<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The wounded-heart, or, The jury-man's offences declared and ingeniously acknowledged for the satisfaction of those who were thereby troubled by Thomas Leader.</title>
            <author>Leader, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11077</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12591013</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12591013</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49874)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 672:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The wounded-heart, or, The jury-man's offences declared and ingeniously acknowledged for the satisfaction of those who were thereby troubled by Thomas Leader.</title>
                  <author>Leader, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
               <term>Assembly, Right of --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63927:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63927:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Wounded-Heart; OR, The Jury—Man's OFFENCES DECLARED, And Ingeniouſly Acknowledged, For the Satisfaction of thoſe who were thereby troubled.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS LEADER.</p>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Prov. 28.13.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q>
               <p>He that covereth his ſins, ſhall not proſper; but whoſo confeſſeth and forſaketh them, ſhall have mercy.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63927:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63927:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Wounded-Heart, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHereas I underſtand that many have been troubled at what hath of late paſt at the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> concerning ſome perſons called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in which Action I was an Inſtrument; I do therefore, for the honour of God, and for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thoſe which are troubled, and unto my own ſhame, write theſe things following, which I do from my whole heart deſire that you would look upon as no feigned thing, but that which doth flow from the abundance of a bleeding-ſoul.</p>
            <p>You have heard that I was one of the Jury upon <hi>January</hi> laſt paſt, when there were ſome perſons, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> to be tryed for the breach of an Act of Parliament, entituled, <hi>An Act to prevent and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Seditious Conventicles,</hi> and upon their Tryals, brought in guilty. Now as to the breach of which Act, you may judge that they were not guilty according to the literal meaning of it; and your trouble, as I underſtand, doth ariſe from this, That I ſhould have a hand in ſuch a thing, which may be to the ruining of many poor ſouls, that are (as I judge) altogether innocent; Now for your ſatisfaction in this caſe, I judge it no leſs than my duty to declare to you, and the whole world, the whole ſtate of the Caſe, which is as followeth: I being ſummoned to appear at <hi>Juſtice-Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old Baily</hi> upon the Jury on the 13th of <hi>January,</hi> I did not uſe that means to get off as otherwiſe I might, and the reaſon of it was this; that much about this time twelve-month I was ſummoned in the like nature, but not impanelled, and ſo I thought I ſhould not now at this time; but herein my expectations failed me, and being miſtaken upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I was impanelled, and did attend upon the buſineſs of the time for two dayes; but before I was on the Jury, I did enquire whether there were any ſuch perſons to be tryed as were called <hi>Quakers?</hi> and I was then informed that there were none, and then I was the more indifferent in the buſineſs: but upon the laſt day of the week I did hear there were ſome ſuch perſons, as is before-mentioned, to be tryed; at the hearing of which I was much troubled, and did not know what to do; and having many reaſonings in my ſelf, I came
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63927:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>to this concluſion, That it was not ſafe for me to uſe means to get off; and that, firſt, becauſe I was called thereunto; alſo ſuppoſing I might be an Inſtrument of good; withal thinking that they were not breakers of that Act, and therefore nothing could be made of it. But for me to relate all thoſe things that paſſed there, is not the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs that is neceſſary in this work, but only this; that when they were called to the Bar, and the Indictment being read, which was <hi>for being at an unlawful Meeting or Conventicle, contrary to the Lytur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the Church of England;</hi> and being asked, <hi>Whether they were guilty, or not guilty?</hi> the anſwer that many of them made was this; <hi>Not guilty of breaking of any righteous Law of God;</hi> others, <hi>that they were innocent,</hi> and the like anſwers were given by them. The Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes being called, they were asked, Whether ſuch and ſuch (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of their names) were at the <hi>Bull and Mouth?</hi> the Witneſſes finding of their names in a Paper which they had in their hands, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>Yes, my Lord, they were there.</hi> Such Evidence as this I thought would be ſtrange and very ſlender, to bring perſons in guilty of the breach of that late Act of Parliament; for the moſt that any of them did ſay, as to what they did there, one of the Witneſſes ſaid, <hi>That they were there a prating.</hi> VVhen the Witneſſes had done, and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners had leave to ſpeak for themſelves, the Judge asked them, Whether they were at the <hi>Bull and Mouth?</hi> ſome of them anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>They were there:</hi> and being asked what they did there? ſome anſwered, <hi>They were there to worſhip God.</hi> Then ſaid the Judge, <hi>It's enough:</hi> And others ſaid, <hi>that they were there, and met in the Fear of God;</hi> he alſo replyed, <hi>That's enough.</hi> But God forbid that any Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers or Governours in the whole world ſhould look upon it as a crime to worſhip God, and to meet in the fear of God. When they had anſwered the Judge in this manner, he told us the buſineſs was ſo clear that we need not go from the place, but that we might give in our Verdict preſently; and moreover, that whereas every one of them was convicted twice before, before two Juſtices of the Peace, we had no more to do, but to find whether they were there or no. But ſome not being willing to make ſo light of a thing of ſuch great concernment, we did (I mean the Jury) all withdraw. When we were altogether, the Fore-man of the Jury did begin to declare his opinion in theſe words, <hi>That the buſineſs was ſo clear we need not ſpend time about it, but go and carry them in guilty.</hi> This was the opinion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63927:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of many. At the hearing of which I told them, that it was not my judgement ſo to do; and although the Eleven were againſt me, I was and muſt be againſt ſuch a Verdict, and my Reaſons for my ſo ſaying, were theſe that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, Becauſe there was no witneſs to prove what they did there: It's true, one of the Witneſſes ſaid, <hi>that they were there a pating.</hi> That Law, as I do underſtand, doth not condemn men for <hi>being at the Bull and Mouth,</hi> neither doth it condemn men <hi>for prating there;</hi> and although they were there, and as they ſaid, <hi>met there in the Fear of the Lord God,</hi> yet I did not judge that it taketh hold on ſuch that ſhal ſo do; becauſe I judged that it was the duty of all men, and in all places, to meet in the Fear of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Reaſon I did then urge was this, That the Act and Indictment ſaith, <hi>contrary to the Lyturgie of the Church of England;</hi> I told them, that for my part I was very ignorant of the Lyturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and being ignorant of it, could not make them guilty of the breach of a thing I knew not, for in ſuch a caſe no man is fit for a Jury-man but what is well-learned in the Lyturgy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Becauſe as I told them, that the Indictment ran, <hi>for being at a Conventicle;</hi> which I told them, That by a Conventicle, as I did underſtand, (for what man can judge more than he knoweth) was a meeting together of ſome perſons for to act againſt the King and Government, but we could not find that any thing was acted there tending unto any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, Becauſe (as I did underſtand) that that Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (as the Judge did inform us) was <hi>to prevent Inſurrections, by meeting together under a Pretence of Religious Exerciſe;</hi> but as unto theſe People they could not be made guilty of the breach of that Act, becauſe there was not any Witneſs to prove that they were there up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>pretence,</hi> but, as they confeſs, <hi>really to worſhip God;</hi> or upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of any Inſurrection; and, as far as ever I could hear, were not the people that ever had hand in any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, I minded this unto them, That the hand of God hath been ſeen in an extraordinary manner, by them that had of late been tranſported, Therefore did adviſe that they would not be raſh, but conſider what it was that they were a going about to do.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons I did uſe, as that which did ſatisfie me, and I thought might have ſatisfied the reſt of the Jury, that the Priſoners
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63927:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>were not guilty of the crimes charged in the Indictment: But all would not ſignifie any thing.</p>
            <p>Now in the conſideration of theſe things, the Officer came and ſaid, <hi>My Lord hath ſent to know whether you are all agreed:</hi> word was ſent, <hi>No.</hi> Many of the Jury ſaid, <hi>That they had confeſſed ſo much, therfore they could do no leſs than carry them in guilty.</hi> I told them often, that I could never agree unto it. The Officer comes again, yet we were not agreed; and goes, and comes again, and ſaid, <hi>My Lord hath ſent me for to lock you up.</hi> At this many of the Jury were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and how to help we could not tell: but at laſt we did begin to conſider, how far we could agree together, and about four of us came to this concluſion, that we could carry them in thus, <hi>That they were at the Bull and Mouth, and upon a Religious account,</hi> and no further; and no more had we, either from the Witneſſes or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: But here all parties were not agreed; and about this time the Officer comes again, and ſaid, <hi>My Lord hath ſent me to know the Names of thoſe that are not agreed.</hi> I then told him my Name, and told him that I could not agree to the bringing of them in guilty of the Indictment. And in this condition we were in for about two hours, about which time thoſe that were for not bringing of them in guilty of the Indictment, did begin to be of another mind, and not only ſo, but did alſo uſe Arguments for to perſwade me; ſo that with what the Judge told us, <hi>That we had nothing to do but to find whether they were there or no;</hi> and alſo with the Officers often coming unto us, and about eight or nine of us that were never upon ſuch a Jury before, and as to my own part I underderſtood but little in ſuch things, and ſo being in a great ſtrait, and reaſoning with my ſelf and others, I was over-perſwaded, and deeply ſurprized, ſo far, as to hold my peace at the Bar, notwithſtanding when that we were a coming out of the room where we were together, I told them that I was not agreed any further than is before-mentioned, and to this ſome of them are my witneſſes; and the Lord of Heaven that knows all hearts, is alſo Witneſs to the truth of this.</p>
            <p>Now this I have to ſay, and do before the Lord, his People, and the whole World, declare, That herein I was ſurprized, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an Inſtrument of great diſhonour unto the Name of God, and a trouble unto his People; and the more I conſider of it, the more I do ſee the wickedneſs of it, and the lowneſs and baſeneſs of my own
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63927:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpirit, that I ſhould be ſilent at ſuch a time, and in ſuch a caſe of ſo great concernment, that was directly againſt my own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which giveth me great cauſe of grief and ſorrow of heart, and doth even cauſe my ſoul to bleed; and the Lord knows it doth diſturb me of my peace by day, and of my reſt by night, That God ſhould give me a Tongue, and yet I ſhould not have a Heart to make uſe of it, in ſuch a caſe, and at ſuch a time! And it hath been often in my thoughts, that if God ſhould deal with me as I have dealt in this caſe, he might deprive me of that member; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I have been a diſhonour unto God, a grief unto the Righteous, a trouble unto my own Soul, and a means of ſorrow and affliction unto many innocent Souls, for want of bearing a Publick Teſtimony when the Lord had put it into my hands; the conſideration of which makes my ſoul to cry out, <hi>O Lord God, what may be done in this caſe!</hi> Sos being under this trouble and ſorrow of heart, for which I may (a I have juſt cauſe) to mourn all the dayes of my life, it came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my heart to write theſe things following, to the end that it might be a Warning unto all men in the like caſe, that when they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto ſuch a work as this was, that they may have a care how they are either perſwaded againſt their own underſtandings, (which as I conceive no mortal man will require) and alſo to know when to ſpeak, how to ſpeak, and when to be ſilent.</p>
            <p>Again, That all men may know I never conſented unto any other Verdict to be brought in againſt thoſe people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than by my ſilence at the Bar, which for the want of a good underſtanding in the work I was then upon, with the Arguments uſed by others, and by often ſending to, and threatning withal, I was ſurprized and led into a ſnare; but yet I thank God that it was not done with premeditation, as <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed his Maſter: yet I dare not excuſe my ſelf, but ſay, <hi>I have ſinned:</hi> and as <hi>Eve</hi> was ſurprized by the ſubtilty of the Serpent, yet it was ſinful in her, and the ſin lay heavy upon her. <hi>Peter</hi> was brought into a ſnare, to deny his Maſter, yet was not to be excuſed from ſin in that caſe. <hi>David</hi> was tempted to number the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet he was not excuſed from ſin, notwithſtanding he was provoked and tempted unto it: and indeed this inſtance of <hi>David</hi> hath la in heavy upon me, that as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did number the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.1, 10. it's ſaid, that <hi>Davids heart ſmote him;</hi> and his heart ſmiting him, was a plain diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63927:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>that he had not done well. Our hearts do not ſmite us when we do thoſe things that are good and right in the ſight of God. And at that very time in which theſe things were done, I was not without a ſmitten heart, and great jealouſies I had that I had not done well, and yet deprived of that reaſon and courage as I ought to have had, to ſay thoſe things which was really my Judgment before. I ſhall not make it my buſineſs to ſay any thing of the faults of others, having too much to ſay of my own; and becauſe I would not be teadious nor burthenſom, I ſhall for the inſtruction of the Chriſtian Reader, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe what I have to ſay into theſe following particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as unto the frame of my own heart, before I was on the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that was thus; I was too too confident in my ſelf, and of my own ſtrength and thoughts, judging the Priſoners were not guilty of the breach of that Act; and from that conſideration concluding that I ſhould not be an Inſtrument to bring them in guilty of it; and here let me tell thee, too much of my own ſtrength did appear, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I was too much like unto <hi>Peter,</hi> when he ſaid, that <hi>though all men forſook Chriſt, yet he would not;</hi> but when he came unto the tryal, he became another man. From hence learn, <hi>That a mans own ſtrength is his exceeding weakneſs, and a mans own confidence is great fooliſhneſs.</hi> Be therefore put in mind alwayes to ſtay upon God; and obſerve this as a certain Rule, That a man being given over to follow his own underſtanding, and to leave the Counſel that proceedeth from above, is ready to work his own ruine, and is like unto a Lamb fed in a large place, ſubject to every devouring Wolf, to be led into every temptation and ſnare of Satan; but the man that doth make the Lord his ſtrength, who giveth himſelf up to be led and guided by him, is a ſafe man: for if floods of temptations ariſe againſt him, yet he hath a Rock under him. And from hence <hi>David</hi>'s confidence did proceed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. That as his <hi>confidence was in God,</hi> and not in his own ſtrength, <hi>he would not fear though the Earth was removed.</hi> Now the end for which I write theſe things is, that no man might be as I have been, too too confident in my own ſtrength: but in all things of concernment, little or much, every man may have his expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from Heaven, that he may walk ſurely therein. Now, from the conſideration of ſuch an eſtate and condition in which I was in (as by woful experience I ſpeak it to my ſhame) in being ſo confident in my own ſtrength, doth put me upon an enquiry into the cauſe and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63927:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>reaſon of theſe things, that I ſhould fall into ſuch a ſnare, which doth indeed make me jealous of my own heart, that it hath not been ſo right to God as it ought, and I deſire to deal plainly in this thing; time was, that it was the rejoycing of my heart to follow the Lord whitherſoever he went, but of late it hath not been ſo; time was that I had greater diſcoveries of God's Love unto my ſoul, but of late I have ſeen to ariſe Miſts and Clouds, and have been as one that hath loſt his firſt Love; and indeed the ſinfulneſs of this wickedneſs is ſo great, that it may give great jealouſies to think I am one that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpued out of the mouth of God: but as to my ſelf I am not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left without hope, becauſe I did it ignorantly. And Chriſt is held forth in the Goſpel not only to be a Saviour from <hi>ſmall offences and ſins,</hi> but <hi>great ſins alſo;</hi> not only to give Grace to <hi>reſtrain</hi> from them, but if any are overtaken by them, he is <hi>an Advocate to plead their cauſe, and to ſave from the guilt and puniſhment of ſin,</hi> if they truly repent. Theſe things I write, not to encourage any in ſin, but to avoid all the appearances of ſin; and not to give way unto a ſpiritual decay, for it will end in miſery. <hi>Peters</hi> confidence was a forerunner of greater miſeries; he denied his Lord, and what followed? <hi>Peter went out and wept bitterly.</hi> And ſo I would it might be a Caution to others, from my experience, to take heed what they do in matters of ſo great concernment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When I was on the Jury, and the Verdict brought in, I was exceedingly troubled in my ſelf, yet at that time not thereby ſenſible wherein I had done amiſs, and that becauſe the Judge told is, that we had no more to do, but to find whether they were at the <hi>Bull and Mouth;</hi> and they confeſſing of it, was the great thing that ſtopped my mouth; but as to the Indictment it ſelf, never otherwiſe perſwaded but that they were not guilty: but being ignorant of my duty in ſuch a work, I held my peace; yet however, my ignorance will not excuſe me; my own peace hath been, and is diſturbed by it, and how I may recover my ſelf, and do good unto thoſe that I have offended (by my ſo acting) I know not: the Lord hath convinced me that I have been an Inſtrument of Unrighteouſneſs in this thing, my heart hath been as an Anvil for Satan to work on, not only to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon, but alſo to baniſh, as who knoweth what may happen unto them, their wives and children, they may cry for vengeance from Heaven; and herein I may ſay, as <hi>David, Its I that have ſinned:</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63927:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and O that God had bleſſed me with that happineſs to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented me! but now it is too late to recal the thing paſt, but <hi>I muſt bear the Indignation of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned against him.</hi> Which leadeth me to the next particular thing, To deſire others that they would <hi>ſympathize</hi> with me; I do not mean in the <hi>ſin,</hi> but in the <hi>ſorrow;</hi> deſiring thoſe that have an intreſt in God, would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it upon my account, that the Guilt might be taken off from me, and that God would ſatisfie me with his Love, whatſoever he ſhould do to me upon any other account. When <hi>Job</hi> was in trouble he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto his Friends to aſſiſt him, <hi>Job</hi> 19.21. <hi>Have pitty upon me, have pitty upon me, O ye my Friends, for the Hand of the Lord hath touched me.</hi> But on the other hand, it was matter of grief unto him, and the adding of ſorrow unto ſorrow, when that they had forſaken him; <hi>Job</hi> 19.14, 19. <hi>All my inward friends abhorred me, and they whom I loved are turned againſt me.</hi> Therefore I deſire that you would aſſiſt in the bearing of the burden with me, and that, if it be the will of God, the Judgment which I may look for, may be prevented, but in a ſpecial manner the Sin forgiven.</p>
            <p>Now that which I have mor to ſay is, That all men might have a care, that whenſoever they may be called unto any work of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, eſpecially when the Honour of God lieth at the ſtake, that you would look well to your hearts; and although you may think you ſtand, yet to tak heed leſt you fall, as I have done, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſnares and temptations, and ſo come to loſe your peace, which is as a precious Jewel of great price: threfore keep your hearts with all diligence; for the neglect thereof leadeth into ſnares: <hi>Thorns and ſnares are in the way of the froward, but he that keepeth his ſoul ſhall be far from them.</hi> The heart of a man is very deceitfull, therefore it is time for a man to look about him, and to have a care of his heart when he thinketh himſlf moſt confident; And God is more honoured by a man that hath a low eſteem of himſelf, than of the other. If he be going about any thing of Concernment, he is very fearful of diſhonouring of God; he is often with God to ask counnſel, often with Friends to take advice, and all is, becauſe he knoweth but a little; He is afraid of diſhonouring God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is very jealous over his own heart. It pleaſed the Lord when he heard <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay, that <hi>he was but a Child,</hi> and therefore he gave him the things he requeſted.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63927:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This I ſpeak to that end that you may be adviſed to lean upon the Lord for advice and counſel, which is the way to keep your eyes from tears, and your feet from falling: but becauſe I took not this counſel my ſelf, I ſhall rather deſire to conclude; onely ſay this, That I look upon what I have here written to be my duty; firſt, to condemn my ſelfe for my ſilence, and that <hi>I</hi> ſhould be ſurprized in ſuch a manner as <hi>I</hi> was; ſecondly, that as <hi>I</hi> have herein committed a publick Offence, ſo <hi>I</hi> judge it my duty to make a publick Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the ſame; and although (as it is poſſible) theſe lines may come into the hands of men of ſeveral Opinions and Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, yet that they would judge charitably of me, that I do it not to pleaſe any man's humour, neither thereby intend to offend any; but as I have offended through my weakneſs, and my ſoul burdened by reaſon thereof, I hope they will all bear with me, conſidering what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. <hi>The ſpirit of a man will ſuſtain his infirmity, but a wounded ſpirit who can bear?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
